<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://parthbatra99.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://parthbatra99.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-11-04T09:23:15+05:30</updated><id>https://parthbatra99.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Parth Batra | batra.blog</title><subtitle>Senior ML Engineer by day, music critic by night. Building ML systems, writing about tech, and collecting spotify minutes like they&apos;re infinity stones.</subtitle><author><name>Parth Batra</name></author><entry><title type="html">I Built a Neovim Plugin in a Language I Don’t Know. Here’s the Story.</title><link href="https://parthbatra99.github.io/2025/11/02/how-i-built-an-ai-powered-neovim-plugin-by-vibe-coding-with-claude.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I Built a Neovim Plugin in a Language I Don’t Know. Here’s the Story." /><published>2025-11-02T12:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2025-11-02T12:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://parthbatra99.github.io/2025/11/02/how-i-built-an-ai-powered-neovim-plugin-by-vibe-coding-with-claude</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://parthbatra99.github.io/2025/11/02/how-i-built-an-ai-powered-neovim-plugin-by-vibe-coding-with-claude.html"><![CDATA[<p>I have a confession to make.</p>

<p>I don’t know Lua. I’ve never written it, I’ve never studied it, and I don’t even have the interpreter installed on my machine.</p>

<p>Yet, over a single weekend, I shipped a Neovim plugin with over 2,800 lines of Lua code, 89% test coverage, and a feature set which a hardcore minimalist neovim guy will appreciate. It’s called <a href="https://github.com/parthbatra99/hexwitch.nvim">hexwitch.nvim</a>, and it lets you generate your editor’s colorscheme from plain English.</p>

<p>This isn’t some 10x developer fairytale. It’s a story about a new way of building software I’m calling “vibe-driven development.” It’s about pairing years of programming fundamentals with an AI to build high-quality projects in languages you’ve never touched. It’s the story of how I used an AI as my product guy and my code monkey - Claude Code, and then had to step in as the adult in the room to make it safe for the public.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/theme-showcase.jpeg" alt="My current neovim theme" /></p>

<h2 id="phase-1-the-idea-guy-and-the-ai">Phase 1: The Idea Guy (and the AI)</h2>

<p>It all started with the classic developer addiction: endlessly tweaking my colorscheme. I had a vague idea: “What if I could just <em>describe</em> a theme?” But the vision was fuzzy. So, before writing a single line of code, I opened a chat with Claude and treated it as my product guy.</p>

<p>We just spitballed. I threw out half-baked ideas, and it threw back refined concepts. We debated features, user flows, and what would make this thing actually cool. What started as a simple “generate a theme” command evolved into a full-fledged vision:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Generate themes from a prompt, obviously.</li>
  <li><em>Refine</em> existing themes with ease (the real magic).</li>
  <li>Save and manage a whole library of your creations.</li>
  <li>Browse themes with a proper UI (because who wants to remember filenames?).</li>
  <li>Support for multiple AI providers, so you’re not locked in.</li>
</ul>

<p>After a few hours, we had a rock-solid plan. The AI didn’t just help me think; it helped me design a better product before a single line of code existed.</p>

<h2 id="phase-2-the-code-monkey---claude-code-also-the-ai">Phase 2: The Code Monkey - Claude Code (Also the AI)</h2>

<p>With a plan in hand, I switched hats. I was now the architect, and Claude was my specialist Lua contractor who only does exactly what they’re told.</p>

<p>I opened a new chat and started directing the work, module by module. The entire plugin was built in a series of 15-20 small, focused conversations.</p>

<p><strong>Me (The Architect):</strong> “Okay, build me a storage module. It needs to save themes as JSON. Give me <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">save_theme</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">load_theme</code> functions. Oh, and sanitize the theme name before you write it to disk.”</p>

<p><strong>Claude (The Lua Specialist):</strong> <em>spits out a perfect little Lua module with everything I asked for.</em></p>

<p>I’d grab the code, run a quick test, and move on.</p>

<p><strong>Me:</strong> “Nice. Now, let’s build a UI. Use Telescope to browse the themes we just saved. Read the JSON files and show them in a list.”</p>

<p>This loop was ridiculously fast. We built the AI provider module, the theme applier, the command registration—each piece in its own little sandbox. I didn’t need to know Lua syntax; I just needed to know how to structure a program and delegate.</p>

<h2 id="phase-3-the-adult-in-the-room-me">Phase 3: The Adult in the Room (Me)</h2>

<p>After a weekend of this, I had a pile of working modules. I stitched them together, debugged the flow, and… it worked. The magic moment of generating a theme from a prompt was real. I had a functional prototype.</p>

<video src="/assets/images/demo-vid.mp4" controls="" style="max-width: 100%; height: auto; border-radius: 8px; box-shadow: 0 4px 6px rgba(0, 0, 0, 0.1);">
  <p>Your browser doesn't support HTML video. Here's a <a href="/assets/images/demo-vid.mp4">link to the video</a> instead.</p>
</video>
<p><em>It’s alive! A live demo of generating a theme from scratch.</em></p>

<p>But here’s the catch: a functional prototype is <strong>not</strong> a secure product. This is where the AI’s job ended and my job as an experienced engineer began.</p>

<p>I put the plugin through a rigorous security audit, and what I found was a glorious, functional, and deeply insecure mess. The AI-generated code was riddled with the exact kind of vulnerabilities you’d expect from a system that just pattern-matches without understanding the consequences. It was time to clean up the mess.</p>

<p>Here’s a summary of the critical fixes I had to implement myself, line by line:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Command Injection:</strong> The AI was building system calls with simple string concatenation. A malicious theme name could have run any command on my machine. I ripped it out and replaced it with parameterized calls.</li>
  <li><strong>Path Traversal:</strong> The AI didn’t sanitize theme names properly, leaving the front door open for an attacker to use <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">../../..</code> to read or write files anywhere on my system. Fixed.</li>
  <li><strong>Malicious Theme Data:</strong> The plugin blindly trusted the theme data from the AI. A malformed theme could have crashed the editor or worse. I added a strict validation layer to sanitize the data before applying it.</li>
  <li><strong>API Key Leakage:</strong> The AI was happily logging my full API key in debug messages. I scrubbed all the logs to make sure no secrets ever saw the light of day.</li>
</ol>

<p>To prove the fixes were solid, I built a security test suite from scratch. The difference was night and day.</p>

<h3 id="security-posture-before-vs-after">Security Posture: Before vs. After</h3>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Issue</th>
      <th>AI-Generated Code (The Intern)</th>
      <th>My Hardening (The Senior Dev)</th>
      <th>Status</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Command Injection</td>
      <td>❌ Wide Open</td>
      <td>✅ Locked Down</td>
      <td><strong>Fixed</strong></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Path Traversal</td>
      <td>❌ Vulnerable</td>
      <td>✅ Protected</td>
      <td><strong>Fixed</strong></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Theme Validation</td>
      <td>❌ YOLO</td>
      <td>✅ Comprehensive</td>
      <td><strong>Added</strong></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>API Key Exposure</td>
      <td>❌ Leaking Secrets</td>
      <td>✅ Sanitized</td>
      <td><strong>Fixed</strong></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Security Tests</td>
      <td>❌ 0%</td>
      <td>✅ 100% Coverage</td>
      <td><strong>Added</strong></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>Only after this manual, expert-led hardening was I confident enough to post <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">hexwitch.nvim</code> on Reddit and not get roasted.</p>

<h2 id="the-result-meet-hexwitchnvim">The Result: Meet <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">hexwitch.nvim</code></h2>

<p>This whole process—AI for vision, AI for code, human for quality—produced a plugin I’m genuinely proud of.</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Generate Themes with Plain English:</strong> <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">:Hexwitch "a moody, high-contrast sci-fi theme with neon green accents"</code></li>
  <li><strong>Iterate and Refine on the Fly:</strong> <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">:Hexwitch refine</code></li>
  <li><strong>Browse Your Creations:</strong> A slick, built-in <a href="https://github.com/nvim-telescope/telescope.nvim">Telescope</a> UI to browse, search, and apply your saved themes.</li>
  <li><strong>Full History with Undo/Redo:</strong> Because creativity needs an escape hatch.</li>
  <li><strong>Bring Your Own AI:</strong> Supports OpenAI, OpenRouter, and custom endpoints out of the box.</li>
</ul>

<p><img src="/assets/images/saved-themes.jpeg" alt="The built-in Telescope UI for browsing your theme library." />
<img src="/assets/images/refine.jpeg" alt="The refine window showing various tweaking configurations." /></p>

<p>It’s a robust tool, and you can install it today:</p>

<div class="language-lua highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="c1">-- With lazy.nvim</span>
<span class="p">{</span>
  <span class="s2">"parthbatra99/hexwitch.nvim"</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="n">dependencies</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="s2">"nvim-lua/plenary.nvim"</span><span class="p">,</span>
    <span class="s2">"nvim-telescope/telescope.nvim"</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="p">},</span>
  <span class="n">config</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="k">function</span><span class="p">()</span>
    <span class="c1">-- Don't forget to set your OPENAI_API_KEY or OPENROUTER_API_KEY!</span>
    <span class="nb">require</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">"hexwitch"</span><span class="p">).</span><span class="n">setup</span><span class="p">({</span>
      <span class="n">ai_provider</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="s2">"openrouter"</span><span class="p">,</span>
      <span class="n">model</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="s2">"anthropic/claude-3-haiku"</span><span class="p">,</span>
    <span class="p">})</span>
  <span class="k">end</span><span class="p">,</span>
<span class="p">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<h2 id="the-scorecard">The Scorecard</h2>

<p>Because I’m an ML engineer at heart, here’s the final tally from my weekend experiment:</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Metric</th>
      <th>Value</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Lines of Lua Written by Me</td>
      <td>0</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Lines of Lua Code Generated</td>
      <td>2,847</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Test Coverage</td>
      <td>89%</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Time Spent</td>
      <td>~48 hours</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Sanity Remaining</td>
      <td>Questionable</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>My Personal Theme Count</td>
      <td>47 (current favorite: “autumn rain in Tokyo”)</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h2 id="my-new-hot-take-ai-is-a-superpower-for-people-who-already-know-their-stuff">My New Hot Take: AI is a Superpower for People Who Already Know Their Stuff</h2>

<p>This experiment fundamentally changed how I see software development. It’s a two-part process:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>AI-Accelerated Prototyping:</strong> Use AI as a hyper-fast intern to turn your architectural vision into code, letting you skip the boring syntax-learning phase.</li>
  <li><strong>Expert-Led Hardening:</strong> Apply your deep human expertise to the critical last 10%—security, performance, and reliability—to turn the prototype into a real product.</li>
</ol>

<p>This is a superpower. It means your value as a developer isn’t just knowing a language; it’s your deep understanding of programming fundamentals that work everywhere. The AI handles the syntax; you handle the safety, quality, and taste.</p>

<h3 id="your-turn">Your Turn</h3>

<p>You have years of experience. What could you build this weekend if you could instantly get a functional-but-insecure v0.9 of any idea? Go try it. The future of development isn’t about replacing us; it’s about amplifying our expertise to ship better, safer products, faster than ever before.</p>

<hr />

<p><em>Check out the project on <a href="https://github.com/parthbatra99/hexwitch.nvim">GitHub</a>. The source code is completely open, and I’d love to see what themes you create!</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Parth Batra</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I have a confession to make.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">When Does Your Streaming Habit Become a Loss for Spotify?</title><link href="https://parthbatra99.github.io/2025/05/23/when-does-your-streaming-habit-spotify.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="When Does Your Streaming Habit Become a Loss for Spotify?" /><published>2025-05-23T17:30:00+05:30</published><updated>2025-05-23T17:30:00+05:30</updated><id>https://parthbatra99.github.io/2025/05/23/when-does-your-streaming-habit-spotify</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://parthbatra99.github.io/2025/05/23/when-does-your-streaming-habit-spotify.html"><![CDATA[<p>For three years running, my Spotify Wrapped has clocked in at over 100,000 minutes. That’s not a flex; it’s a confession. It’s more than two full months of non-stop audio, and it got me thinking: at what point does my obsession become a money pit for Spotify?</p>

<p>Am I a dedicated super-listener, or am I just a freeloader in disguise?</p>

<p>So, I did what any ML engineer with a music obsession would do: I dove into the numbers. My guinea pig? The Indian market—a place with some of the most ridiculously low subscription prices in the world. If I was going to be a freeloader anywhere, it would be here.</p>

<p>Let’s get into it.</p>

<h3 id="part-1-the-revenue-the-money-spotify-makes-off-you">Part 1: The Revenue (The Money Spotify Makes Off You)</h3>

<p>Spotify’s pricing in India is… aggressive. To give you some perspective, a Premium plan in the US is $10.99. In India, it’s ₹139, which is roughly <strong>$1.40</strong>.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> That’s a massive difference, and it’s the first key to our puzzle.</p>

<p>Here’s a quick breakdown of what you pay and what Spotify <em>actually</em> pockets per user on their most common plans:<sup id="fnref:1:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup></p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th style="text-align: left">Plan Tier</th>
      <th style="text-align: left">Monthly Price (INR)</th>
      <th style="text-align: left">Users</th>
      <th style="text-align: left">Effective Revenue Per User (INR)</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>Premium Individual</strong></td>
      <td style="text-align: left">₹139</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">1</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>₹139.00</strong></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>Premium Student</strong></td>
      <td style="text-align: left">₹69</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">1</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>₹69.00</strong></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>Premium Duo</strong></td>
      <td style="text-align: left">₹179</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">2</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>₹89.50</strong></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>Premium Family</strong></td>
      <td style="text-align: left">₹229</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">6</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>₹38.17</strong></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>The Family plan is the real kicker. If you max it out with six people, Spotify is making about ₹38 per person. That’s barely the cost of a fancy coffee. They also run wild promotional deals, like a full year of Premium for ₹499 during Diwali,<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup> which drops the monthly revenue for an individual to just <strong>₹41.58</strong> (about 50 cents).</p>

<p>This isn’t a bug; it’s a feature. Spotify is playing the long game: get everyone hooked now, figure out how to make more money later.</p>

<h3 id="part-2-the-costs-the-money-spotify-spends-on-you">Part 2: The Costs (The Money Spotify Spends on You)</h3>

<p>This is where it gets interesting. Spotify doesn’t just pay artists a fixed fee. Instead, they use a “pro-rata” model. Think of it like a pizza party.</p>

<ol>
  <li>Spotify gathers all the money from subscriptions and ads in India into one giant pizza.</li>
  <li>They take their cut first (about 30% of the pizza).</li>
  <li>The remaining 70% is the “royalty pizza” for all the artists.</li>
  <li>This pizza is then sliced up based on who got the most streams. More streams, bigger slice.</li>
</ol>

<p>Because the revenue pizza in India is smaller, the slices are naturally smaller. After digging through a bunch of sources, the most solid estimate for India is about <strong>$0.0008 per stream</strong>.<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup></p>

<p>Converting that to INR, we get our magic number: <strong>₹0.07 per stream</strong>.</p>

<p>This is the <em>marginal cost</em>—the direct cost of you listening to one more song.</p>

<h3 id="round-1-the-break-even-point">Round 1: The Break-Even Point</h3>

<p>Okay, we have the revenue and the cost. Time for some simple math.</p>

<p><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Break-Even Streams = Monthly Revenue / Cost Per Stream</code></p>

<p>Let’s see what that means in terms of your daily listening habit:</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th style="text-align: left">Plan Tier</th>
      <th style="text-align: left">Daily Listening to Break Even (Marginal Cost)</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>Premium Individual</strong></td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>~4.0 hours/day</strong></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>Premium Student</strong></td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>~2.0 hours/day</strong></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>Premium Duo</strong></td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>~2.6 hours/day</strong></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>Premium Family</strong></td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>~1.1 hours/day</strong></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>If you’re on a Family plan, listening for just over an hour a day makes you a <em>marginal loss</em> for Spotify. For a solo user, it takes a more respectable 4 hours—basically a part-time job.</p>

<p>But wait, there’s more.</p>

<h3 id="part-3-the-real-cost-the-boring-stuff-that-actually-matters">Part 3: The <em>Real</em> Cost (The Boring Stuff That Actually Matters)</h3>

<p>Here’s the thing: royalties are just one piece of the pie. Spotify is a massive tech company with huge overheads. They spend a fortune on:</p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Research &amp; Development (R&amp;D):</strong> Paying all those engineers to build things like the AI DJ and keep the lights on.</li>
  <li><strong>Sales &amp; Marketing (S&amp;M):</strong> All those ads and campaigns to get new users.</li>
</ul>

<p>In Q2 2025 alone, they spent a combined <strong>€779 million</strong> on this stuff.<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup> To figure out the <em>true</em> cost of a user, we need to allocate a slice of that overhead to every subscriber.</p>

<p>After running the numbers from their quarterly reports, the global overhead cost comes out to about <strong>₹38.60 per subscriber, per month</strong>.</p>

<p>This is the “fully-loaded” cost, and it’s a game-changer.</p>

<h3 id="the-final-showdown-the-real-break-even-point">The Final Showdown: The <em>Real</em> Break-Even Point</h3>

<p>Let’s redo our calculation. Your subscription fee needs to cover both the royalty cost <em>and</em> your share of the overhead.</p>

<p>With an average user streaming about 600 songs per month, the overhead allocation comes to about <strong>₹0.064 per stream</strong>.</p>

<p>So the total, fully-loaded cost per stream is ₹0.07 (royalty) + ₹0.064 (overhead) = <strong>₹0.134 per stream</strong>.</p>

<p>Now let’s see the <em>real</em> break-even points:</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th style="text-align: left">Plan Tier</th>
      <th style="text-align: left">Daily Listening to Break Even (Fully-Loaded Cost)</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>Premium Individual</strong></td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>~2.6 hours/day</strong></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>Premium Student</strong></td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>~1.3 hours/day</strong></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>Premium Duo</strong></td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>~1.7 hours/day</strong></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>Premium Family</strong></td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>~0.7 hours/day</strong> (that’s just 42 minutes!)</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>To truly cost Spotify money, an individual user has to be streaming for <strong>about two and a half hours. Every. Single. Day.</strong> And on the dirt-cheap Family plan, you only need to be locked in for <strong>42 minutes</strong> daily before you’re in the red.</p>

<h3 id="so-whats-the-punchline">So, What’s the Punchline?</h3>

<p>It’s actually <em>way easier</em> than you might think to be a freeloader on Spotify.</p>

<p>The entire business model is built on a system of <strong>cross-subsidization</strong>. The millions of casual users who listen for 30-60 minutes a day are footing the bill for the more dedicated listeners, and yes, even “super-listeners” like me.</p>

<p>Spotify isn’t trying to maximize profit from every single user, especially not in a strategic growth market like India. Their game plan is clear: capture market dominance, become the default audio app, and then gradually increase revenue through pricing power and new features.</p>

<p>So, am I costing Spotify money with my 100k+ minutes a year?</p>

<p>Nope. Not even close. It turns out my listening habit isn’t just tolerated—it’s exactly the kind of engagement they’re betting on for long-term growth.</p>

<h3 id="sources">Sources</h3>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>All subscription pricing data is from Spotify’s official website for the Indian market as of October 2025. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a> <a href="#fnref:1:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;<sup>2</sup></a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p>Based on a promotional offer reported by publications like The Times of India for Diwali 2025. <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:3">
      <p>This per-stream payout rate is an estimate for the Indian market from industry analysis by sources like Lost Stories Academy. Currency conversion uses $1 = ₹87.5 (approximate 2025 rate). <a href="#fnref:3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:4">
      <p>Combined Research &amp; Development and Sales &amp; Marketing expenses, as reported in Spotify’s official Q2 2025 earnings release. Overhead allocation calculated as €779M ÷ 602M global subscribers ÷ 3 months = ₹38.60 per subscriber monthly. <a href="#fnref:4" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name>Parth Batra</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[For three years running, my Spotify Wrapped has clocked in at over 100,000 minutes. That’s not a flex; it’s a confession. It’s more than two full months of non-stop audio, and it got me thinking: at what point does my obsession become a money pit for Spotify?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">I Resurrected a 12-Year-Old Keyboard, and It’s Now My Daily Driver</title><link href="https://parthbatra99.github.io/2025/03/02/first-keyboard-that-i-made-weekend-diy.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I Resurrected a 12-Year-Old Keyboard, and It’s Now My Daily Driver" /><published>2025-03-02T09:59:00+05:30</published><updated>2025-03-02T09:59:00+05:30</updated><id>https://parthbatra99.github.io/2025/03/02/first-keyboard-that-i-made-weekend-diy</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://parthbatra99.github.io/2025/03/02/first-keyboard-that-i-made-weekend-diy.html"><![CDATA[<p>My Keychron K8, a <strong>perfectly respectable</strong> modern mechanical keyboard, is currently serving as a <em>very expensive</em> dust cover. For the past three months, it’s been sitting in my office, <strong>completely ignored</strong>.</p>

<p>The culprit? A <strong>12-year-old TVS Gold</strong> I unearthed from a forgotten box while shifting homes. I should have thrown it out. It was <em>disgusting</em>. But now, it’s the <strong>only keyboard I want to use</strong>.</p>

<h3 id="the-archaeological-dig">The Archaeological Dig</h3>

<p>Opening this thing up was less of a tech project and more of a <strong><em>hazmat situation</em></strong>. A <strong>decade of neglect</strong> had turned the inside into a fluffy graveyard of dust, grime, and things I don’t want to identify. It was <em>crusty</em>.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/step1.jpeg" alt="Opening the keyboard, cleaning the internals, and fixing the wiring." /></p>

<p>After a vigorous session with a brush and compressed air, I plugged it in. Nothing. Of course. I was ready to call it a day, but then I saw the connector pins. They were green with corrosion.</p>

<p>A bit of IPA, some <em>creative rewiring</em>, and a prayer later, I plugged it in again.</p>

<p><strong>It worked.</strong> Every single key. This <strong>old tank</strong> was still kicking.</p>

<h3 id="decontamination-protocol">Decontamination Protocol</h3>

<p>With the guts <em>surprisingly functional</em>, it was time to face the <strong>horror of the exterior</strong>. The plastic frame was a mottled, Jackson Pollock-esque mess of grey and black. It looked like it had been stored in a swamp.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/step2.jpeg" alt="The discolored and degraded plastic frame of the keyboard." /></p>

<p>This is where <strong>my weekend disappeared</strong>. I dismantled the entire keyboard. The board cleaned up nicely, but the keycaps were a <em>special kind of hell</em>.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/step3.jpeg" alt="The cleaned keyboard circuit board." /></p>

<p>I scrubbed <strong>every single keycap by hand</strong>. It was <em>tedious, soul-crushing work</em>. My fingers were raw. My spirit was nearly broken. But I was in <strong>too deep to stop</strong>.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/step4.jpeg" alt="Cleaning each keycap individually." /></p>

<h3 id="keyboard-heresy-and-questionable-lubricants">Keyboard Heresy and Questionable Lubricants</h3>

<p>The keys worked, but they felt <em>awful</em>—stiff, scratchy, and loud in all the wrong ways. They needed lube. On a modern board, I’d desolder the switches and do it properly. But this was a <strong>12-year-old board</strong> I’d just barely coaxed back to life. My soldering skills are, let’s say, <strong><em>developing</em></strong>. I wasn’t about to risk its life.</p>

<p>So, I committed a <strong><em>cardinal sin</em></strong> in the eyes of keyboard purists. I grabbed a syringe and some Rubik’s cube lube I had lying around.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/step5.jpeg" alt="Using a syringe to apply lube to the key switches." /></p>

<p>I can hear the <strong>gasps from here</strong>. But guess what? It worked <em>beautifully</em>. The keys are now <strong>buttery smooth</strong>, with a deep, satisfying <em>“thock”</em> that modern boards just can’t replicate.</p>

<h3 id="the-car-detailing-trick">The Car Detailing Trick</h3>

<p>The frame was still a problem. It was clean, but the plastic was faded and sad. I’d seen people try all sorts of weird retro-brighting techniques, but I had a different idea. I reached for the ceramic wax I use on my car.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/step6.jpeg" alt="Applying ceramic wax to the plastic frame to restore its color." /></p>

<p>The result was <strong>genuinely shocking</strong>. The wax didn’t just shine it up; it restored the <strong>deep, rich black</strong> of the plastic. It looks <em>almost new</em>.</p>

<h3 id="the-aftermath">The Aftermath</h3>

<p>After a weekend of grime, <em>questionable hacks</em>, and a lot of patience, the <strong>TVS Gold was reborn</strong>. It’s been my <strong>daily driver for three months</strong>, and I’m not looking back. It’s a <em>joy to type on</em>, and it gets <strong>more comments than any fancy gadget I own</strong>.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/step7.jpeg" alt="The fully restored TVS Gold mechanical keyboard, looking like new." /></p>

<h3 id="the-sound-of-victory">The Sound of Victory</h3>

<p>The <strong>best part</strong>, though, is the <strong>sound</strong>. This keyboard has the <em>original blue switches</em>, and they are <strong>magnificent</strong>. They have a <em>crisp, clicky, tactile feedback</em> that’s been lost in most modern keyboards. Here’s a sample:</p>

<audio controls="">
  <source src="/assets/audio/tvs_gold.m4a" type="audio/mpeg" />
  Your browser does not support the audio element.
</audio>

<p>This is the <strong>quality TVS was famous for</strong>. Their new switches feel <em>mushy and cheap</em> in comparison. It’s a shame, but it makes me <strong>all the more grateful</strong> I was able to save this one.</p>

<p>So yeah, my fancy wireless keyboard is taking a <strong>long vacation</strong>. Sometimes the best tech isn’t the newest or the shiniest. It’s the <strong>old workhorse</strong> you rescue from a dusty box and <strong>bring back from the dead</strong>.</p>

<p><em>I’m sure the Keychron understands.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Parth Batra</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[My Keychron K8, a perfectly respectable modern mechanical keyboard, is currently serving as a very expensive dust cover. For the past three months, it’s been sitting in my office, completely ignored.]]></summary></entry></feed>